Guide to the Jay and Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers TAM.083
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Jay Leyda Papers, 464819
  - Subseries D: Cinema, Soviet, 80156
    - Soviet film clippings, Brandon Film Studio Catalog; 1960s, 80164 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Soviet film clippings in Russian; 1930-70s, 1930-1970; 80163 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - "Soviet Scientific and Educational Cinematography" (USSR Society for Cultural Relations With Foreign Countries), 1949; 80162 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - "Soviet Silent Cinema Retrospective Pacific Film Archive", Oct 1- Dec 13, 1973; 80161 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - "State Institute of Cinematographie" - curriculum; c. 1933-36, ca.1933-1936; 80160 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - UNRA: "In the Wake of the Armies", 1945; 80159 (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - "USSSR Association of Film Makers" Conference in Moscow, 1973; 80158 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Waldekranz, Rune "The Influence of Soviet Cinema in Sweden"; 1970s, 80157 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Subseries E: Other Projects, 80062
    Subseries E: Other Projects principally documents the balance of Leyda's cinema career as educator, curator, and author, and contains several film scripts, lectures and articles, research notes and clippings, reviews, and some correspondence, including that with the Guggenheim Foundation, 1931-42, regarding his fellowship application. The file on A Bronx Morning contains a partial list of film shots. There are Leyda scripts for unproduced movies, including World Unity (1940s) and Conquistador (1943). The file on Bartelby the Scrivener includes scripts, and there is also some correspondence and publications relating to Leyda's work on Melville and Dickinson. There are several files which contain "Germinations," i.e., various project proposals, and several typescripts by novelist and poet Ben Maddow.
    - "A Bronx Morning" (Leyda's first film), 1931-1979; 80155 (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - African-Americans in American Film (film list), 1945-1973; 80154 (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - "American Night" WWII Projects (typescripts), undated; 80153 (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - Armstrong Gallery; 1970s?, ca.1970-1979; 80152 (Box 21, Folder 24)
    - "Bartleby" Opera by Jay Leyda (drafts and scripts), 1954-1964; 80151 (Box 21, Folder 25)
    - "Bartleby" Opera by Jay Leyda (progam and reviews), 1964; 80150 (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - "Bartleby" Opera by Jay Leyda (notes and typescripts); c. 1960s, ca.1960-1969; 80149 (Box 21, Folder 27)
    - Chaplin, Charlie (Newspaper clippings, script by Charlie Chaplin), 1931-1964; 80148 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Children's books: examples of modern Russian art; c. 1930s, ca.1930; 80147 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - "Compilation Film" research notes 1; 1960s - 70s, 1960-1979; 80146 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - "Compilation Film" research notes 2; 1960s - 70s, 1960-1979; 80145 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Conference "American-Russian Cultural Exchange" (UCLA Westwood), 1945; 80144 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Conference "Emily Dickinson Sequicentenniel Conference & Concert", 1980; 80143 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Conference "Film and Photo League", 1934; 80142 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Conference "On the Use of Audiovisual Archives as Original Source Materials", 1972; 80141 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Conference "US in the World", 1976; 80140 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Conference "Writers Congress" (CLA Westwood), 1943; 80139 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Conferences, talks - Leyda as a speaker (programs), 1933-1978; 80138 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Dickinson, Emily: published material by Jay Leyda, 1955-1957; 80137 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Dickinson, Emily: reference material, drafts, correspondence, 1952-1987; 80136 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Dickinson, Emily: reviews, 1960; 80135 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - "Dictionary of Politics and Film" (Projects); c. 1972, ca.1972; 80134 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - "Direction": Jay Leyda advisory editor for film (5 issues), 1939-1942; 80133 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Exhibition "Art of the American Negro", 1940; 80132 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Exhibition "Before Hollywood" (curated by Leyda), 1983-1986; 80131 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Film, African (notes, newspaper clippings), undated; 80130 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Film, Czech (notes, review), undated; 80129 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - "Film begets Film" (newspaper clippings), 1964-1967; 80128 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - "Film begets Film" (notes, German edition), 1967; 80127 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Film Correspondence, 1939-1940; 80126 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - "Film Center Gazette", 1978-1979; 80125 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Film, general reference material 1; 1960s - 70s, 1960s -19 70s; 80124 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Film, general reference material 2; 1960s-70s, 1960s-1970s; 80123 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Film, German (leaflets, programs), 1955-1982; 80122 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Film, Japanese (notes, articles, lists), 1969-1973; 80121 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - "Film Music Series": tentative programs, undated; 80120 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Films - leaflets, programs etc.; 1970s, 80119 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - "Film Quarterly" (notes, drafts, correspondence), undated; 80118 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - "Film Quarterly" (notes, drafts, correspondence), 1933-1945; 80117 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Film script "Animation - An Art for the Future?" (John Hubley), 1974; 80116 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Film script "Automatic Gain Control", undated; 80115 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Film script "Conquistador" (Jay Leyda & Anne Green), 1943; 80114 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Film script "Erzahlungen aus der Neuen Welt" (DEFA), 1968; 80113 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Film script: Film on Russian-American Friendship (Jay Leyda), undated; 80112 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Film script: Melville Film, 1978-1979; 80111 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Film script "Rhoda", undated; 80110 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Film script "The Green Island", undated; 80109 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Film script "World Unity" (Jay Leyda); 1940s, 1940-1949; 80108 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Films found and to be found, mostly Dutch (notes), undated; 80107 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Germany: State Film Archives, GDR (correspondence, work agreement), 1964-1965; 80106 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Griffith, D.W., 1936-1975; 80105 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation - fellowship application, 1931-1942; 80104 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Guild Theatre (program themes), undated; 80103 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - "Heroes" A Farce by Jay Leyda & Leo T. Hurwitz, 1951; 80102 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Hollywood lectures on film, 1945-1946; 80101 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - International Film Seminars Minutes; 11-May-79, 1979; 80100 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Kafka, Franz (Clippings, photos, notes), undated; 80099 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Lecture & class notes, 1969-1981; 80098 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Maddow, Ben "A Sunday Between Wars" (typescript), 1984; 80097 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Maddow, Ben "Psalm of Twelve Fridays" (typescript), undated; 80096 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Maddow, Ben (seasonal greetings/writings), undated; 80095 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Maddow, Ben "The Glass Poet" (typescript), undated; 80094 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Melville articles by Jay Leyda, 1948-1985; 80093 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Melville correspondence, 1967-1986; 80092 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - "Melville Log" dust cover, book reviews, 1951; 80091 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Melville (reference material), 1949-1985; 80090 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Metcalf, Paul: series of readings, undated; 80089 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Meyer, Carl "A Tribute to Carl Meyer (1894-1944)" pamphlet, 1947; 80088 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Meyers, Sidney "Vision is my Dwelling Place" by Jay Leyda, 1969; 80087 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Mills, Constance Quinby "A String of Pearls" (poems), 1963; 80086 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous ("Germinations") project proposals, notes 1, undated; 80085 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous ("Germinations") project proposals, notes 2, undated; 80084 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous typescripts by various authors; 1970s - 80s, ca.1970-1989; 80083 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes by Jay Leyda, undated; 80082 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Jay Leyda, undated; 80081 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Jay Leyda, 1930-1979; 80080 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Mussorgsky (correspondence, articles by Jay Leyda); 1940s, 1940-1949; 80079 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - National Board of Review of Motion Pictures; c. 1933, ca.1933; 80078 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - New School: course on film making, 1938-1939; 80077 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - New York University: courses, flyers, newspaper clippings, 1974-1982; 80076 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Photography: Leyda as photographer, 1932-1935; 80075 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Project proposal for study in Japan, undated; 80074 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Proposal to Col. Frank Capra; 1942?, ca.1942; 80073 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Rachmaninoff: "Sergey Rachmaninoff: A Lifetime in Music" book reviews, 1966; 80072 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Realist Film News (Australian newsletter), 1956; 80071 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Script Magazine: Clippings on Stage and Screen by A. Jopfin (Leyda aka?), 1947; 80070 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Swigmore, Douglas: "Selections from the Lone Pine Book of Modern Verse"; c. 1973, ca.1973; 80069 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Strohheim, Erich von; c. 1973, ca.1973; 80068 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - "Voices of Film Experience" proposal, reviews, 1974-1977; 80067 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - "Voices of Film Experience" book proposal, contract; c. 1973-78, ca.1973-1978; 80066 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Weinberg, Herman G. "The Man with the Movie Camera", 1966; 80065 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Yale University (faculty list), 1970; 80064 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - York University courses on film of Asia & Africa, 1972; 80063 (Box 27, Folder 17)
- Series II: Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers, 464821
  The Si-Lan Chen Leyda papers document her dancing career and personal activities. The small biographical subseries contains her FBI file, and documents related to her travels. Si-Lan Chen's correspondence is principally with her family and Jay Leyda. There is also correspondence with Pearl S. Buck and Langston Hughes, and a file relating to immigration issues. Her dance career is documented by programs, flyers, dance notations and drawings, a scrapbook, and radio interview transcripts. Her writings include the typescript of her autobiography, Footnote to History (1984), a diary, autobiographical notebooks, and unpublished writings.
  - Subseries A: Biographical, 80056
    - FBI-file and correspondence, 1944-1979; 80061 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - FBI-file, 1952-1971; 80060 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Passports - British, Chinese, 1932-1943; 80059 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Soviet Union documents, 1931-1935; 80058 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - United States documents, 1942; 80057 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence, 80033
    - Correspondence (envelopes); 1930s-40s, ca.1930-1949; 80055 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence (general), 1929-1986; 80054 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Buck, Pearl S., 1942; 80053 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Chen, Carmen, 1945; 80052 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Chen, Eugene, 1929-1944; 80051 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Chen family misc., 1931-1938; 80050 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Chen, Jack, 1931-1985; 80049 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Chen, Jay, 1982-1984; 80048 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1929-1941; 80047 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1942-1946; 80046 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Chen, Yolanda, 1947-1983; 80045 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Chen, Yuan Tsung, 1971-1987; 80044 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Ewen, Kay (Kathleen); 1980s, 1980-1989; 80043 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1933-1946; 80042 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Immigration issues, 1926-1978; 80041 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Leyda, Jay, undated; 80040 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1933-1935; 80039 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1936-1940; 80038 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1941-1944; 80037 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Leyda, Jay, 1946-1973; 80036 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Pilgrim, Philip, 1941-1942; 80035 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Rene, Natalie, 1929-1950; 80034 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Subseries C: Dance and Other Activities, 80025
    - Chinese dance and drama, 1970; 80032 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Dance notes, notation, undated; 80031 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Programs, flyers, tickets; 1930s, 1930-1939; 80030 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Programs, flyers, tickets; 1940s, 1940-1949; 80029 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Radio interview transcripts, 1938-1948; 80028 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Reviews, press comments; 1930s-40s, 1930-1949; 80027 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Scrap book (newspaper clippings), 1932-1939; 80026 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Subseries D: Writings, 80009
    - Address and note books, undated; 80024 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Articles by Si Lan Chen, 1941-1982; 80023 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Chen, Jack: Articles and writings, 1938-1950; 80022 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Chen, Jack: Drawings, 1933-1936; 80021 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Diary, 1942; 80020 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - "Footnote to history" (correspondence), 1942; 80019 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 1, undated; 80018 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 2, undated; 80017 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 3, undated; 80016 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - "Footnote to history" (typescript) 4, undated; 80015 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Printed Sheet Music and Handwritten Scores, undated; 464946 (Box 32)
    - "The road to Peking: an idea for a Hope-Crosby-Lamour film" (typescript); 1943 [?], ca.1943; 80014 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 1, 1936; 80013 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 2, 1936; 80012 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - "The summer of my life" (autobiographical notebook) Vol. 3, 1941; 80011 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Unpublished writings, undated; 80010 (Box 31, Folder 11)
- Series III: Photographs and Graphics, 464847
  The photographs and graphic materials series provides documentation of several stages in the lives of Jay Leyda and Si-Lan Chen. It is particularly strong in childhood and family snapshots of each including a small photograph album from each family. There are portraits and snapshots of the pair in the 1930s when they first met. Other highlights in the collection are a series of photoprints by Jack Chen, Si-Lan's brother, taken in China, probably during the mid-40's; an article with photographs in the War Worker (May 1944, Los Angeles) about Si-Lan Chen's dancing; photoprints of the 1964 "Bartelby" production at Oberlin (Leyda wrote the libretto for Aschaffenburg's opera); studio performance and movie production shots of Si-Lan; a snapshot of Luis Bunuel and his sister, Conchita in 1969 at a cottage near Madrid; and a group of graphics and photoprints collected for "Dianyang."
  - Art Photographs (Photographed by Jay Leyda), 1929-circa 1930; 465009 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Art Photographs (Taken by Jay Leyda), 1929-1930; 465024 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - "Bartelby" Production Photographs, 1964; 465026 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Ben Maddow Photographs and Poem "A Wedding Hymn", undated; 465028 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Art Works, undated; 465029 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - "Dianying", circa 1968-1972; 465031 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Dickinson Family Silhouettes, 1955, undated; 465033 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - "Footnote to History" Photographs, Negatives, and Graphics, circa 1930s-1960s, undated; 465035 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Jack Chen Photographs, undated; 465036 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Jane Reece Portraits of Jay Leyda, circa 1928; 465037 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Jay Leyda Portraits and School Pictures, undated, 1934, 1960; 465039 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Jay Leyda at Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers Award Luncheon, 1984; 465041 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Kafka's Grave and Luis Bunuel, 1969; 465043 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - "Liberation News Service" Cover, December 4, 1971; 465045 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Med Hondo (Meg Xohgo?) Negatives and Transparencies, 1984; 465047 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Moscow Art Theatre Negatives, undated; 465048 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - New York Scenes, 1850s-1860s; 465051 (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Personal: Family and Friends, 1920s-1940s, 1960s, undated; 465053 (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - "Photos 1928-1947", 465055 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Photo Album, undated; 465057 (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - Photo Album, undated; 465058 (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Photo Album, Moscow (includes note by Jack Chen), May 1928; 465060 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - Pin and Ribbon, 1960; 478293 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - "Russian Painting 1700-1917" by Jack Chen, 1948; 465064 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Si-Lan Chen Miscellaneous, undated; 465065 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Si-Lan Chen Movie Production Stills, circa 1946; 465067 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Si-Lan Chen Portraits, undated; 465069 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Si-Lan Chen Studio Performance Shots, undated; 465071 (Box 34, Folder 5-7)
  - Stamps, undated; 465072 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - "Stills for Russian Film?", circa 1920s; 465073 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Woman, undated; 465074 (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Watercolors and Drawings: Loose Items, undated; 465076 (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Watercolors and Drawings: Notebooks, undated; 465077 (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - "The War Worker" (Featuring Article on Si-Lan Chen), 1944; 464950 (Box OS001)
  - Si-Lan Chen: Portrait, Posters (in Spanish), and Group Photograph, undated; 464827 (Box OS001)
  - Films: "Printed Sheet Music and Hand-printed Scores", 1974-08 (Reel 1, Reel 2)